<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Post-rsses on Birdr</title>
    <link>http://blog.birdr.co.uk/post/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Post-rsses on Birdr</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-gb</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 13 Dec 2016 10:28:43 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://blog.birdr.co.uk/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Welcome</title>
      <link>http://blog.birdr.co.uk/post/welcome/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 Dec 2016 10:28:43 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://blog.birdr.co.uk/post/welcome/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve been curious about bird watching my whole life. Both my parents are keen twitchers and I was often taken on thinly-veiled &amp;lsquo;holidays&amp;rsquo; to cold &amp;amp; windy places all in the pursuit of finding some obscure little brown bird. As I&amp;rsquo;ve grown older I&amp;rsquo;ve found myself becoming fascinated with trying to build software to improve a bird watchers life, which I&amp;rsquo;ve come to refer to as &lt;em&gt;birdtech&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my opinion, bird watching is a hobby that is perfectly suited to technology. It is a hobby based on recording bird sightings including date &amp;amp; time, location and photographs - things that a modern smartphone excels at. Despite this, very little (decent) software exists for bird watchers. There are a host of listing tools, most of which are clunky desktop applications or overly complicated for all but the most avid &lt;em&gt;listers&lt;/em&gt;. Over the past 10 years I&amp;rsquo;ve made several attempts to change this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;i-b-i-s&#34;&gt;I.B.I.S.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My first foray into the world of birdtech was back in 2003 during my undergraduate degree. As part of a module on A.I. I wrote a &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lisp_(programming_language)&#34;&gt;LISP&lt;/a&gt; program called the Intelligent Bird Identification System (I.B.I.S.). The premise behind I.B.I.S. was that a bird watching novice could enter a number of details about a bird they could not identify and the system would inform them of what they had seen. Ironically, I.B.I.S. was neither intelligent nor could it identify any birds. Nonetheless, the seed was planted and my passion for birdtech was born.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;i-b-i-s-ii&#34;&gt;I.B.I.S. II&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During my final year of university in 2006 I re-branded I.B.I.S. into the Integrated Bird Information System. Despite its spectacularly vague name, I.B.I.S. II was far more useful. It was a clunky desktop application (written in &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/C_Sharp_(programming_language)&#34;&gt;C# .NET&lt;/a&gt;) that allowed a bird watcher to add their records on a map. The application would then produce lists for you, such as &lt;em&gt;year lists&lt;/em&gt;. Technically speaking it was quite a complex application. I effectively ended up building Google maps in OpenGL&amp;hellip; only limited to the Greater Peterborough area!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;birdr&#34;&gt;Birdr&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Birdtech took a back seat in my life for some years while I focused on my Ph.D., but in 2011 it came back with a vengeance. Together with a friend, &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/itszootime&#34;&gt;Richard Jones&lt;/a&gt;, I started work on our first Web-based birdtech application. &lt;a href=&#34;http://birdr.co.uk/&#34;&gt;Birdr&lt;/a&gt; was an excuse for me and Richard to spend time learning a new technology, &lt;a href=&#34;http://rubyonrails.org/&#34;&gt;Ruby on Rails&lt;/a&gt;, while working on a project that interested us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Birdr allowed a user to record their sightings on Google maps, as well as add photos, create bird clubs, comment, like and various other interactions you&amp;rsquo;d expect from a modern application. We had a trial run with a few Peterborough Bird Club members and it was generally well-received. After a year of development we ceased working on it for reasons I can&amp;rsquo;t recall. A real shame.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;birdlists-and-friends&#34;&gt;BirdLists and friends&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following on from birdr I&amp;rsquo;ve created several other birding Websites, all in Ruby on Rails. The first of these is &lt;a href=&#34;http://birdlists.me/&#34;&gt;BirdLists&lt;/a&gt;. The premise of BirdLists was to simplify the somewhat complicated interface of birdr into something even my dad could use (literally).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My latest app is a bespoke site for the &lt;a href=&#34;http://nenbc.co.uk/&#34;&gt;North East Norfolk Bird Club (NENBC)&lt;/a&gt;. This started off in the same vein as BirdLists but with additional club-based functionality. However, over the years we&amp;rsquo;ve progressively added new functionality so that it is almost identical to where birdr was 5 years ago!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Throughout the years I have made several attempts at recreating birdr, but none have ever made it off the ground.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;no-more-please&#34;&gt;No more, please!&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite birdr failing to take off, I still believe there is scope for a birding community site. I think part of the reason birdr (and subsequent mutations) have failed is that I always saw it as an opportunity to make money. I would often get bogged down by trivial matters such as &amp;ldquo;How much should we charge?&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;Which features should be premium?&amp;rdquo; On reflection, the most valuable thing I got out of birdr was the opportunity to learn new technologies inside and out. It is a project of sufficient scope that it requires an in-depth knowledge of the tech which is an invaluable learning aid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, this time I am going to approach birdr not as a means to make money, but as an opportunity to learn new skills and improve myself as a programmer. On that note, all source code produced will be open source - as in free - and I will document my journey here on this blog. Who knows, perhaps I will find a like-minded individual to share the journey with.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>