<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>About-rsses on Birdr</title>
    <link>http://blog.birdr.co.uk/about/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in About-rsses on Birdr</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-gb</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 13 Dec 2016 17:00:56 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://blog.birdr.co.uk/about/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>About</title>
      <link>http://blog.birdr.co.uk/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 Dec 2016 17:00:56 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://blog.birdr.co.uk/about/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://blog.birdr.co.uk/images/about.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;A picture of me on top of Cairngorm&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Birdr was born out of two lifelong interests: birding and computing. While I can’t say I’m an avid birder, I’ve spent enough time in hides and by rubbish tips to appreciate the &lt;a href=&#34;https://trevorontour.me/&#34;&gt;love my parents have for birdwatching&lt;/a&gt;. Tech, on the other hand, is my passion. Having built my first website at the age of 13 I’ve never looked back. I studied Computer Science at university, obtained a Ph.D and, more recently, had the opportunity to work on &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.bbc.co.uk/iplayer&#34;&gt;BBC iPlayer&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the past decade I have built &lt;a href=&#34;http://birdlists.me/&#34;&gt;numerous&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;http://nenbc.co.uk/&#34;&gt;bird watching&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;http://blog.birdr.co.uk/post/welcome-to-birdr/&#34;&gt;websites&lt;/a&gt; - some more successful than others. This blog is documenting my latest attempt - to build the world’s largest birding community. I will use Birdr as an opportunity to learn new tech, such as: &lt;a href=&#34;https://golang.org/&#34;&gt;Go&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.docker.com/&#34;&gt;Docker&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://kubernetes.io/&#34;&gt;Kubernetes&lt;/a&gt;. Over the course of it’s development I will provide updates on progress, as well as attempting to explain these technologies to the bird watchers among you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re interested in getting involved in the project, either as a birder or a developer, feel free to &lt;a href=&#34;mailto:matt@birdr.co.uk&#34;&gt;get in touch&lt;/a&gt;. If you’d like to know more about my background, check out &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/in/matthew-williams&#34;&gt;my profile&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>